export const jambEnglish = [
  // First Comprehension
  {
    comprehension: `
          One of the interesting things to me about spaceship is that it is a mechanical vehicle, just as an automobile. If you own a car, you realize that you must put oil and gas into it, and you must put water in the radiator and take care of the car as a whole.
          You begin to develop quite a little thermodynamic sense. You know that you are either going to have to keep the machine in good order or it is going to be in trouble and fail to function.
          We have not been seeing our Spaceship Earth as an integrally designed machine which to be persistently successful, must be comprehended and serviced in total.
          Now there is one outstanding important fact regarding Spaceship Earth, and this is that no instruction book came with it. I think it is very significant that there is no instruction book, for successfully operating our ship, in view of the infinite attention to all other details displayed by our ship.
          It must be taken as deliberate and purposeful that an instruction book was omitted. Lack of instruction has forced us to find out that there are two kinds of mangoes – unripe mangoes that will kill us and ripe mangoes which will nourish us.
          And we had to find out ways of telling which-was-which mangoes before we ate it or otherwise we would die. So we were forced, because of this, to devise scientific experimental procedures and to interpret effectively the significance of the experimental findings. Thus, because the instruction manual was missing, we are learning how we can safely survive on the planet.
          Quite clearly, all living beings are utterly helpless at the moment of birth. The human child stays helpless longer than the young of any species.
          Apparently, it is part of ‘invention' that man is meant to be utterly helpless through certain anthropological phases. When he begins to be able to get on a little better, he is meant to discover some of the physical principles inherent in the universe as well as the many resources around him which will further multiply his knowledge.
          Designed into this Spaceship Earth's total wealth was a big safety factor. This allowed man to be very ignorant for a long time until he had amassed enough experiences from which to extract progressively the system of generalized principles governing the increase of energy. The design omission of the instruction book forced man to discover retrospectively just what his most important capabilities are.
          He learned to generalize fundamental principles of the universe.
        `,
    instruction: "Read the passage below and answer the questions:",
    questions: [
      {
        question:
          "According to the writer, the exciting thing about Spaceship Earth is that",
        options: [
          "has no instruction manual",
          "it is not difficult to maintain",
          "is peculiar to other automobiles",
          "is relatively easy to operate",
        ],
        answer: "has no instruction manual",
      },
      {
        question: "The absence of instruction manual in Spaceship Earth has",
        options: [
          "made the operation of the Spaceship Earth difficult",
          "forced man to devise other means of travelling in spacecraft",
          "challenged man's inquisitiveness",
          "made man helpless",
        ],
        answer: "challenged man's inquisitiveness",
      },
      {
        question: "From the passage, it can be deduced that man",
        options: [
          "learns by experiment and education",
          "learns by chance and accidentally",
          "is incapable of solving all his problems",
          "by his nature is in constant search of knowledge",
        ],
        answer: "by his nature is in constant search of knowledge",
      },
      {
        question: "The writer's mood in the passage is that of",
        options: ["non-committal", "pessimism", "optimism", "frustration"],
        answer: "non-committal",
      },
    ],
  },

  // Second Comprehension
  {
    comprehension: `
      Stress is by far the most common cause of ill health in our society, and may be the underlying cause of as many as 70-80% of all visits to family doctors. It is also the problem that every doctor shares with patients.
      Experts note that stress is an issue everyone can relate to experimentally. In studying and better understanding about stress, we can derive personal as well as professional benefits.
      Stress can be overcome without undergoing duress. They often say anyone who wants to help someone deal with his/her stress should learn to handle his/hers first. The manifestations of stress are legion. It can contribute or mimic just about any symptom you can think of. However, the main symptoms are physical, mental, emotional and behavioural.
      The causes of stress are multiple and varied but they can be classified into external and internal. External stressors can include relatively getting sick or dying, jobs being lost or people criticising or one becoming angry. However, most of the stress people experience is self-generated.
      Experts tell us that we create the majority of our upset indicating that because we cause most of our own stress, we can do something about it. This gives us a measure of choice and control that we do not always have when outside forces act on us. This also leads to a basic premise about stress reduction.
      To master stress-change, you have to figure out what you are doing that is contributing to your problem and change it. These changes fall into behaviour, thinking, lifestyle choices and / or situations you are in. By getting to the root cause of your stress, you can prevent recurrences.
      As a way of draining off stress energy, nothing beats aerobic exercise. To understand why, we need to review what stress is. People often think of stress as pressure at work, a demanding boss, a sick child or rush-hour traffic.
      These may be triggers but stress is actually the body’s reaction to factors such as these. Stress is the fight-or-flight response in the body, mediated by adrenaline and other stress hormones, and comprises such physiologic changes as increased heart rate and blood pressure, faster breathing, muscle tension, dilated pupils, dry mouth, and increased blood sugar. In other words, stress is the state of increased arousal necessary for an organism to defend itself at a time of danger.
      Exercise is the most logical way to dissipate the excess energy. It is what our bodies are trying to do when we pace around or tap our legs and fingers. It is much better to channel it into a more complete form of exercise like a brisk walk, a run, a bike ride, or a game of squash.
      Just as we are all capable of mounting up and sustaining a stress reaction, we have also inherited the ability to put our bodies into a state of deep relaxation called the ‘relaxation response’.
      In this state, all the physiologic events in the stress reaction are reversed. Pulse slows, blood pressure falls, breathing slows, and muscles relax.
    `,
    instruction: "Read the passage below and answer the questions:",
    questions: [
      {
        question:
          "The expression, … stress is an issue everybody can relate to experimentally, means that",
        options: [
          "it is better understood when experienced",
          "its problem can be solved by everybody",
          "everybody avoids it",
          "everybody encounters it",
        ],
        answer: "it is better understood when experienced",
      },
      {
        question: "Which of the following is true according to the passage?",
        options: [
          "Stress is mostly caused by internal factors",
          "Stress can only be avoided during relaxation",
          "Stress is better handled by the individual",
          "The issues of stress can be solved with no effort",
        ],
        answer: "Stress can only be avoided during relaxation",
      },
      {
        question:
          "According to the passage, the major step in controlling stress is",
        options: [
          "changing one’s attitude to stressors",
          "understanding the history of disease",
          "visiting family doctors for check-up and treatment",
          "constant exercise to dissipate every energy",
        ],
        answer: "changing one’s attitude to stressors",
      },
      {
        question: "The experts feel one can control one’s stress because",
        options: [
          "its causes are understandable",
          "it is not difficult to control",
          "external factors contribute less stress",
          "it is individually initiated",
        ],
        answer: "it is individually initiated",
      },
      {
        question: "From the passage, it can be deduced that stress is",
        options: [
          "hormonal disorder in the body system",
          "individually induced problems",
          "bodily reaction to internal factors",
          "bodily reaction to external factors",
        ],
        answer: "individually induced problems",
      },
    ],
  },

  // Third Comprehension
  {
    comprehension: `
      There are many indicators with which to assess or measure corruption. One of them is the affluent living habit of the public official compared to his/her income. 
      Corruption occurs when a public official expects to be induced to perform an act which that public official is ordinarily required to do by law. 
      Corruption can slow down development. One of the most widely discussed consequences of corruption is the distortion of governmental expenditure. This often results in public money being wasted on white elephant projects, rather than people-oriented services, such as health and education. 
      As a result, more opportunities are presented for corrupt use or diversion of funds. Raising the ethical standard of governance can lead to many benefits especially for the economic, political and social development of a country. 
      Fighting corruption and promoting governance is therefore crucial to developing an environment that facilitates the social, political and economic development of the people. 
      However, while there are often general statements made about the effect of corruption on poverty and development, there is not an explicit recognition that corruption is more than just wealth misappropriation or abuse of power. 
      Corruption impoverishes countries and deprives their citizens of good governance. It destabilizes economic systems. When crime and other illegal activities flourish, basic public functions are eroded and the quality of life of the people is reduced. 
      Bribery, for example, is universally regarded as a crime, but it also reflects socio-economic problems that require broad-based preventive measures, and the involvement of society at large. 
      Another implication of global measures against corruption is making government work better by improving the economy. 
      Finally, redesigning political and regulatory structures will reduce corruption and other anti-system players that encourage corrupt practice.
    `,
    instruction: "Read the passage below and answer the questions:",
    questions: [
      {
        question: "According to the writer, corruption is triggered off by",
        options: [
          "unnecessary affluence",
          "selfish interest",
          "private officials",
          "public officers",
        ],
        answer: "unnecessary affluence",
      },
      {
        question:
          "From the passage, one of the consequences of corruption is that",
        options: [
          "large projects are executed",
          "it is beneficial to wealthy people who stole public wealth",
          "it impedes the progress of a nation",
          "people get what they want with so much money to spend",
        ],
        answer: "it impedes the progress of a nation",
      },
      {
        question: "Who, according to the writer, should prevent corruption?",
        options: [
          "Lawyers and Police",
          "Corrupt public officers",
          "The government",
          "The people",
        ],
        answer: "The government",
      },
      {
        question:
          "Which of the following is an indication of ethical standard of governance?",
        options: [
          "Fundamental human right",
          "Socio-economic instability",
          "Democratic governance",
          "Bloated expenditure",
        ],
        answer: "Democratic governance",
      },
      {
        question:
          "The essence of fighting corruption, according to the passage, is to",
        options: [
          "send the corrupt to yell",
          "promote good governance",
          "punish corrupt politicians",
          "make people richer",
        ],
        answer: "promote good governance",
      },
    ],
  },

  // Normal Questions
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, select the options that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question:
      "Though Mr. Iro is a new chairman, he views other members with jaundiced eye.",
    options: [
      "He takes a rather forceful position on dealing with his members.",
      "He takes an unfavourable position concerning his members.",
      "He takes a sickly view of his members.",
      "He takes a rather hazy view of his members.",
    ],
    answer: "He takes an unfavourable position concerning his members.",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, select the options that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question: "People are not interested in who rules.",
    options: [
      "People are not ruled by the leaders they want.",
      "People are not concerned about who rules them.",
      "The rulers are not concerned about the people.",
      "People who rule are not interested in the ruled.",
    ],
    answer: "People are not concerned about who rules them.",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, select the options that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question: "It was good to steer a middle course in whatever one does.",
    options: [
      "It is always good to get midway in anything one does.",
      "It is always good to act with moderation.",
      "It is always good to move away from the forefront.",
      "It is always good to work very hard.",
    ],
    answer: "It is always good to act with moderation.",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, select the options that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question: "The witness said he had no axe to grind with his brothers.",
    options: [
      "He had no hatred for the brothers.",
      "He had no axe and therefore stole the matchet.",
      "He had no axe and therefore borrowed their matchet.",
      "He had no vested interest in the brothers.",
    ],
    answer: "He had no hatred for the brothers.",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, select the options that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question: "The footballers moved with their tails between their legs.",
    options: [
      "They moved happily because they won the match.",
      "They were unhappy because they had been despised by their opponents.",
      "They were ashamed because they had been defeated.",
      "They moved with their tails between their legs.",
    ],
    answer: "They were ashamed because they had been defeated.",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, select the options that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question:
      "The headmaster managed to talk his way out of having to give a speech.",
    options: [
      "He delivered a speech despite the difficulty.",
      "He managed to give a speech out of a difficult situation.",
      "He managed to get himself out of a difficult situation.",
      "He managed to talk on his way.",
    ],
    answer: "He managed to get himself out of a difficult situation.",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, select the options that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question: "As regards the matter, we have crossed the rubicon.",
    options: [
      "We are completely at a loss.",
      "We are irrevocably committed.",
      "We are already qualified.",
      "We are perfectly committed.",
    ],
    answer: "We are irrevocably committed.",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, select the options that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question: "Uche is full of himself.",
    options: [
      "He is conceited.",
      "He is complete.",
      "He is a rich man.",
      "He is careful.",
    ],
    answer: "He is conceited.",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, select the options that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question:
      "As debutants in that tournament, the Super Eagles were up against their first opponents by three goals to nill.",
    options: [
      "The Super Eagles were playing in the tournament for the first time, but they won their match by three goals to nothing.",
      "Though the Super Eagles were rated as the weakest side in the tournament, they won their first match by three goals to nill.",
      "Even though the Super Eagles were playing without some of their regulars, they won their match by three goals to nill.",
      "As the best attackers in the match, the Super Eagles easily defeated their opponents by three goals to nothing.",
    ],
    answer:
      "The Super Eagles were playing in the tournament for the first time, but they won their match by three goals to nothing.",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, select the options that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question: "The woman was mournful as her husband was found dead drunk.",
    options: [
      "She was sad because her husband was absolutely drunk.",
      "She was apprehensive that her husband would drink again as soon he recovered from the drunken stupor.",
      "She was sad because her husband was drunk and always as helpless as a dead man.",
      "She was mourning because her husband drank and died.",
    ],
    answer:
      "She was sad because her husband was drunk and always as helpless as a dead man.",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of question, choose the options opposite in meaning to the word or phrase.",
    question:
      "I am optimistic about the interview though it was a mind bending exercise.",
    options: ["An enervating", "A debilitating", "A difficult", "An easy"],
    answer: "An easy",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of question, choose the options opposite in meaning to the word or phrase.",
    question: "The trader was amused by the cut-throat rush for the goods.",
    options: ["Worrisome", "Strange", "Lacklustre", "Mad"],
    answer: "Lacklustre",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of question, choose the options opposite in meaning to the word or phrase.",
    question:
      "The teacher said that Ali’s essay was full of many redundant details.",
    options: ["Unexplained", "Strange", "Necessary", "Useful"],
    answer: "Necessary",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of question, choose the options opposite in meaning to the word or phrase.",
    question: "His father surmounted the myriad of obstacles on his way.",
    options: ["Most", "Few", "All", "Many"],
    answer: "Few",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of question, choose the options opposite in meaning to the word or phrase.",
    question: "Her ingenuous smile drew our attention.",
    options: ["Witty", "Naïve", "Clever", "Arrogant"],
    answer: "Arrogant",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of question, choose the options opposite in meaning to the word or phrase.",
    question: "Ndeni gave a flawless speech at the party.",
    options: ["A wonderful", "A careless", "An interesting", "An imperfect"],
    answer: "An imperfect",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of question, choose the options opposite in meaning to the word or phrase.",
    question: "Beneath Ado’s guff exterior, he’s really very kind-hearted.",
    options: ["Nice", "Harsh", "Rough", "Gentle"],
    answer: "Harsh",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of question, choose the options opposite in meaning to the word or phrase.",
    question:
      "The captain says sports is being debased by commercial sponsorship.",
    options: ["Localized", "Perverted", "Elevated", "Overvalued"],
    answer: "Elevated",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of question, choose the options opposite in meaning to the word or phrase.",
    question:
      "Governing a country is not always as straightforward as people sometimes imagine.",
    options: ["Complicated", "Troublesome", "Untoward", "Irksome"],
    answer: "Complicated",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of question, choose the options opposite in meaning to the word or phrase.",
    question: "The crowd was very receptive to the speaker’s suggestion.",
    options: ["Disobedient", "Repellent", "Alert", "Hostile"],
    answer: "Hostile",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of question, choose the options opposite in meaning to the word or phrase.",
    question: "There was a general acquiescence on the new drug law.",
    options: ["Resistance", "Discrepancy", "Compromise", "Agreement"],
    answer: "Resistance",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of question, choose the options opposite in meaning to the word or phrase.",
    question: "Aisha seems to feel ambivalent about her future.",
    options: ["Decisive", "Anxious", "Ambitious", "Inconsiderate"],
    answer: "Decisive",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of question, choose the options opposite in meaning to the word or phrase.",
    question: "The report of the committee contained a plethora of details.",
    options: ["Shortage", "Simplicity", "Multitude", "Spectrum"],
    answer: "Shortage",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of question, choose the options opposite in meaning to the word or phrase.",
    question: "The weather was still very heavy and sultry.",
    options: [
      "Wintry and shadowy",
      "Cold and friendly",
      "Cloudy and thundery",
      "Hot and uncomfortable",
    ],
    answer: "Cold and friendly",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of question, choose the options opposite in meaning to the word or phrase.",
    question: "Ada gave her husband a look that made words superfluous.",
    options: ["Redundant", "Spurious", "Unnecessary", "Scanty"],
    answer: "Scanty",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question:
      "A political Impasse does not offer the best opportunity for merrymaking.",
    options: ["manifesto", "party", "gridlock", "rally"],
    answer: "gridlock",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question:
      "We were all enthusiastic as we awaited the result of the election.",
    options: ["bemused", "agitated", "elated", "nervous"],
    answer: "agitated",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "The uniform makes the guards look absurd.",
    options: ["dirty", "smart", "sensible", "ridiculous"],
    answer: "ridiculous",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "The law is often tardy in reacting to changing attitude.",
    options: ["quick", "slow", "exclusive", "generous"],
    answer: "slow",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "Isa and llu ate sumptuous meal on their brother’s wedding day.",
    options: ["expensive", "foreign", "insipid", "cheap"],
    answer: "expensive",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "Kaltume crouched over the paper on her desk.",
    options: ["wrote on", "stood on", "walked over", "bent over"],
    answer: "bent over",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question:
      "The panacea for a country’s economic mess lies in systematic planning and hard work.",
    options: ["cure", "hope", "foresight", "trouble"],
    answer: "cure",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question:
      "Thousands of workers have been victims of retrenchment since the military came back to power.",
    options: [
      "Unemployment",
      "Trench mentality",
      "Suffering",
      "Increase in penury",
    ],
    answer: "Unemployment",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "The principal gave his speech offhand at the sports meeting.",
    options: ["calmly", "beautifully", "unconcerned", "unprepared"],
    answer: "unprepared",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "Jankoli was dressed in an old assortment of clothes.",
    options: ["Avalanche", "Homogeneity", "Sameness", "Melange"],
    answer: "Melange",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question:
      "The girl’s father was astounded to see her appear from the shrine.",
    options: ["collected", "Overwhelmed", "embarrassed", "Astonished"],
    answer: "Astonished",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question:
      "The director’s remark was extremely apposite to the issue being discussed.",
    options: ["Appropriate", "Inconsequential", "Emphatic", "Adequate"],
    answer: "Appropriate",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "Her reputation is without a blemish.",
    options: ["Struggle", "Problem", "Fault", "Blessing"],
    answer: "Fault",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "Ugo is eligible for the post of secretary.",
    options: ["Nominated", "Invited", "Qualified", "Intelligent"],
    answer: "Qualified",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "This is an abridged version of No Longer at Ease.",
    options: ["An outdated", "An enlarged", "An illustrated", "A shortened"],
    answer: "A shortened",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option that best completes the gap(s).",
    question: "Lemoti……… as a painter, but also as a sculptor.",
    options: [
      "is a gifted only not",
      "is only not gifted",
      "is gifted not only",
      "is only gifted",
    ],
    answer: "is gifted not only",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option that best completes the gap(s).",
    question:
      "He can recall the important dates in the nation’s history, it is interesting to listen as he rattles ………",
    options: ["off", "over", "up", "out"],
    answer: "off",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option that best completes the gap(s).",
    question: "The boy told his mother ……..",
    options: [
      "that was the girl he told her about",
      "that was the girl I told you about her",
      "that was the girl I told her about",
      "that is the girl he told her about",
    ],
    answer: "that was the girl he told her about",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option that best completes the gap(s).",
    question: "Last Monday his father asked me ……..",
    options: [
      "if I had come some days before",
      "if I had come the day before",
      "did you come yesterday",
      "had I come yesterday",
    ],
    answer: "if I had come the day before",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option that best completes the gap(s).",
    question:
      "His wife was badly injured in the fracas, but I think she will pull …….",
    options: ["up", "over", "through", "back"],
    answer: "through",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option that best completes the gap(s).",
    question:
      "A wide range of options …….. made available to students in the final year last year.",
    options: ["is", "were", "are", "was"],
    answer: "was",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option that best completes the gap(s).",
    question:
      "One of the women who …….. in the premises ……. been ordered to quit.",
    options: ["sells/have", "sell/has", "sell/have", "sells/has"],
    answer: "sells/has",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option that best completes the gap(s).",
    question: "The new trade agreement should facilitate………",
    options: [
      "more economic rapid growth",
      "economic more rapid growth",
      "rapid economic more growth",
      "more rapid economic growth",
    ],
    answer: "more rapid economic growth",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option that best completes the gap(s).",
    question: "The principal said that he was pleased……… my effort.",
    options: ["on", "of", "with", "about"],
    answer: "with",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option that best completes the gap(s).",
    question: "Paper is made……. Wood pulp.",
    options: ["on", "of", "from", "with"],
    answer: "from",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option that best completes the gap(s).",
    question: "Long after everyone…….. the hall, Obi still sat inside.",
    options: ["left", "is leaving", "has left", "had left"],
    answer: "had left",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option that best completes the gap(s).",
    question: "They are the…….. dresses.",
    options: ["babys’", "baby", "babies", "babies’"],
    answer: "babies’",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option that best completes the gap(s).",
    question: "The politician was sent……. Exile.",
    options: ["onto", "into", "on", "to"],
    answer: "into",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option that best completes the gap(s).",
    question: "When we looked up, we…….. the plane some miles away.",
    options: ["site", "cited", "sited", "sighted"],
    answer: "sighted",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option that best completes the gap(s).",
    question:
      "Vital….. is still spread….. word of mouth in most villages in Africa.",
    options: [
      "information/from",
      "information/with",
      "information/by",
      "information/through",
    ],
    answer: "information/by",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option that best completes the gap(s).",
    question: "Western education is one of the….. of colonial rule.",
    options: ["legacies", "evidence", "remnants", "inheritance"],
    answer: "legacies",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option that best completes the gap(s).",
    question: "The federal government has…… child trafficking.",
    options: ["postulated", "projected", "prescribed", "proscribed"],
    answer: "proscribed",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option that best completes the gap(s).",
    question:
      "The man was happy that his son confessed his guilt and so the others were……",
    options: ["Implicated", "accused", "punished", "exonerated"],
    answer: "exonerated",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option that best completes the gap(s).",
    question:
      "Based on the facts before me, I have no alternative…… to hold you responsible.",
    options: ["only", "as", "than", "but"],
    answer: "but",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions, choose the option that best completes the gap(s).",
    question: "Many people would always find reasons to……the law.",
    options: ["arrogate", "debase", "circumvent", "circumspect"],
    answer: "circumvent",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option that has the same vowel sound as the one represented by the letters underlined.",
    question: "Coup",
    options: ["whup", "hoot", "couple", "scout"],
    answer: "hoot",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option that has the same vowel sound as the one represented by the letters underlined.",
    question: "Indict",
    options: ["bright", "fish", "pick", "brick"],
    answer: "bright",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option that has the same vowel sound as the one represented by the letters underlined.",
    question: "Roared",
    options: ["towered", "coast", "brought", "rod"],
    answer: "towered",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option that has the same consonant sound as the one represented by the letter(s) underlined.",
    question: "Sheath",
    options: ["bathe", "length", "months", "paths"],
    answer: "length",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option that has the same consonant sound as the one represented by the letter(s) underlined.",
    question: "High",
    options: ["what", "honest", "who", "vehicle"],
    answer: "who",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option that has the same consonant sound as the one represented by the letter(s) underlined.",
    question: "Of course",
    options: ["plough", "dough", "over", "orphan"],
    answer: "over",
  },
  {
    comprehension:
      "In 1962, a team of scientists produced a special radio station that had a range of fifteen miles. Even though communication was being accomplished in space at a range of more than a million times this distance, the new radio station caused much excitement among scientists. The reason: its power supply was a ‘battery’ made of bacteria. For the first time, practical amounts of electricity were being produced by a form of life and put to use. Bio cell, the new power supply, had a liquid fuel containing tiny forms of life that changed the fuel directly into electric energy; this was far more than an interesting experiment. The bio cell is being developed as producers of electricity for radio, for signals to guide ships, for lighting, and other uses. Though the working bio cell is only a few years old, some scientists feel that it will one day produce power as cheaply as is now being done by other methods, and that the bio cell will use materials that would otherwise be considered waste. Early bio cells were powered with sugar, but a wide range of fuels can be used. Work is being done using seawater to feed the bacteria. Electricity from living cells is not a new idea. Man experienced the strange shock produced by some fish even before electricity was really discovered. Then in time, there were other discoveries. Benjamin Franklin found that lightning in the sky was electricity. Luigi Galvani found some electricity in the muscles and nerves of animals, but the African catfish produces far more electricity than most other living creatures. The electric eel is also well-named for its even greater electric charge. Researchers also discovered that even humans produce small amounts of electricity in their bodies. Our hearts produce very small amounts that can be measured, as do our brains. The bio cell is completely new in the field of power production, and as yet, no mass-production models have begun to replace older types of batteries. It might be wondered, then, what the excitement is all about.",
    instruction: "Answer the following questions based on the passage above.",
    questions: [
      {
        question:
          "The writer’s posture, as conveyed in the statement 'Electricity from living cells is no new idea', can be described as",
        options: ["Ineffectual", "Contentious", "Logical", "Unguarded"],
        answer: "Logical",
      },
      {
        question: "Which of the following is true according to the passage?",
        options: [
          "Scientists felt that bio-cells would produce very costly energy",
          "Bio-cells, at the beginning, derived their energy from sugar",
          "Sugar and fuel were initially used as sources of energy for bio-cells",
          "Bio-cells were forms of power used by the scientists",
        ],
        answer: "Bio-cells, at the beginning, derived their energy from sugar",
      },
      {
        question:
          "The inventor of bio-cells justified the need for it by saying that it would",
        options: [
          "develop ways for changing bio-cells into fuel for use",
          "yield a source of energy without much spending",
          "produce electricity for all types of machines",
          "produce signals to guide all ships and other vessels",
        ],
        answer: "yield a source of energy without much spending",
      },
      {
        question:
          "According to the passage, electricity was first discovered in",
        options: [
          "heart and brains",
          "muscles of animals",
          "lightning",
          "fish",
        ],
        answer: "lightning",
      },
    ],
  },
  {
    comprehension:
      "Though assumption is the lowest level of knowledge, it is still a form of knowledge, and knowledge is key. Assumptions are the foundation upon which interpretation and conclusion are built. Everything in life operates under certain assumptions. We make management decisions based on the assumptions we hold about how management ought to function and how people ought to be governed. For some of us, we consciously imbibe assumptions and principles about life and consciously decide based on them; for others, it is unconsciously but potent all the same. Our assumptions will either drown us or help us soar through life. We have always seen life as an immense mansion with many rooms. Some rooms lead to wealth, others to the opposite. Ultimately, we decide where we end up; and life, thus far, has proved that not everyone of us decides well, we all behave differently where we have different levels of understanding and behave the same way where our understanding is the same. We eat because we all understand the consequences of not eating. We all wear clothes because each of us comprehends lunacy. The list goes on and on. It is inevitable that some of us will make choices that get and keep us on the lower rung of the ladder by reason of exposure, training or other variables. Life is about role-playing. We choose our roles wisely or foolishly, consciously or unconsciously. Some of us get wiser to new levels of self-awareness enough to redefine our roles, while others make no effort to build further capacity and therefore remain where they are. It is based on those realities that we draw the conclusion that not everyone will be wealthy in life. We lead, inspire, and motivate people to strive and succeed. It is also important that we paint the full and true picture of life so that we can discourage vain pursuits. Balance must be enthroned as a critical component of truth, and people know, for instance, that 'the top' is not a place that all must ascend. Our greatest consolation lies in our deep conviction that true prosperity is in fulfillment through hard work than in intangible acquisition. There are set roles that some of us have been wired up to play in life but which we are not content enough to play because society esteems such roles to be inferior. Take the almost sacred office of a teacher for instance; there are people who have the natural gifts and inclinations to be school teachers. But the teaching profession, as it is, does not appear to be lucrative. So we have people who could have been more fulfilled and effective working as school teachers serving in banks.",
    instruction: "Answer the following questions based on the passage above.",
    questions: [
      {
        question:
          "According to the writer, people lead and motivate others because they want to",
        options: [
          "project individual contribution",
          "encourage selfless service",
          "make the world a home",
          "prevent empty search",
        ],
        answer: "prevent empty search",
      },
      {
        question:
          "According to the passage, balance must be enthroned because it is",
        options: [
          "a critical interdependent function",
          "an amazing help for conscience",
          "a critical part of fidelity",
          "a serious way of ensuring success",
        ],
        answer: "a critical part of fidelity",
      },
      {
        question: "The word 'inclinations', as used in the passage, means",
        options: ["creeds", "tendencies", "inhibitions", "power"],
        answer: "tendencies",
      },
      {
        question:
          "Which of the following statements is true according to the passage?",
        options: [
          "greatness in life emerges when square pegs are put in round holes",
          "people do certain things in life because they know the repercussion",
          "people agree on all issues and behave the same way for the same reason",
          "understanding life at different levels gives no account of visible acquisition",
        ],
        answer:
          "people do certain things in life because they know the repercussion",
      },
      {
        question: "From the passage, it can be inferred that",
        options: [
          "People insincerely discuss facts that govern their behaviour",
          "all managerial decisions are based on assumptions",
          "people make conscious efforts to acquire hidden knowledge",
          "all things in life exist on some beliefs",
        ],
        answer: "all things in life exist on some beliefs",
      },
    ],
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question: "If he were here, it could be more fun.",
    options: [
      "He was expected but did not show up to make the occasion lively.",
      "There was no fun because he was not present.",
      "He did not show up and so the occasion lacked much fun.",
      "He was being expected to supply more fun.",
    ],
    answer: "He was expected but did not show up to make the occasion lively.",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question:
      "The secretary said that the postponement of the meeting was due to unforeseen circumstances.",
    options: [
      "The date of the meeting was shifted as a result of unexpected reasons.",
      "The meeting’s date was put off for strange reasons.",
      "The meeting was called off as a result of obstacles hitherto unknown.",
      "The meeting broke off as a result of unusual difficulties.",
    ],
    answer:
      "The date of the meeting was shifted as a result of unexpected reasons.",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question: "The hunter has a bird’s-eye view of the animals.",
    options: [
      "He views the animal from a high position.",
      "He views the bird’s eye.",
      "He views the birds on the tree with one eye.",
      "He watches animals and birds closely.",
    ],
    answer: "He views the animal from a high position.",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question:
      "Even though Susan was the last in the examination, her result wasn’t too different from what had been expected.",
    options: [
      "Her result was poor.",
      "Her result was a disappointment.",
      "Her result was as expected.",
      "She had not been serious with her studies.",
    ],
    answer: "Her result was as expected.",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question: "Mrs. Adasu does all her work with more haste, less speed.",
    options: [
      "She accepts whatever she does with more haste and speed.",
      "She approaches whatever she does hurriedly.",
      "She addresses everything she does very quickly to avoid mistakes.",
      "She does everything carefully to avoid mistakes.",
    ],
    answer: "She approaches whatever she does hurriedly.",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question: "She stopped her education as her uncle left her in the lurch.",
    options: [
      "Her uncle deceived her.",
      "Her uncle disinherited her.",
      "Her uncle refused to help her.",
      "Her uncle disrespected her.",
    ],
    answer: "Her uncle refused to help her.",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question:
      "The plan to upgrade the dispensary to a general hospital did not materialize.",
    options: [
      "The plan did not meet the required specifications.",
      "The arrangement did not work out as wished.",
      "It was difficult to obtain the materials.",
      "The materials purchased were not the right ones.",
    ],
    answer: "The arrangement did not work out as wished.",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question: "Okon’s company took a hit last year.",
    options: [
      "His company improved last year.",
      "His company made a huge success last year.",
      "His company was badly damaged last year.",
      "His company was established last year.",
    ],
    answer: "His company was badly damaged last year.",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question: "My eldest son, who is in Lagos, is studying English.",
    options: [
      "Only my son is in Lagos studying English.",
      "My only son is in Lagos studying English.",
      "One of my sons is in Lagos studying English.",
      "My sons are in Lagos but only one is studying English.",
    ],
    answer: "One of my sons is in Lagos studying English.",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question: "If I went to the village, I would visit the king.",
    options: [
      "If I go to the village I will visit the king.",
      "I did not go to the village and I did not visit the king.",
      "All the times I went to the village I also visited the king.",
      "I will visit the king when I go to the village.",
    ],
    answer: "If I go to the village I will visit the king.",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrases that's asterisked.",
    question:
      "Since its *inception* in 1983, the newspaper has attracted thousands of readers.",
    options: ["renaissance", "coming", "commencement", "publication"],
    answer: "commencement",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrases that's asterisked.",
    question: "Mrs. Asio wanted her sister to stop being so *detached*.",
    options: ["friendly", "careless", "indifferent", "passionate"],
    answer: "friendly",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrases that's asterisked.",
    question: "Lantana *dwelt* in a ruined cottage on the hillside.",
    options: ["sat", "worked", "slept", "lived"],
    answer: "lived",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrases that's asterisked.",
    question: "The mistake brought the show to an *ignominious* end.",
    options: ["a good", "a palatable", "a disgraceful", "a satisfactory"],
    answer: "a disgraceful",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrases that's asterisked.",
    question: "He *compliments* me on my way of doing things.",
    options: ["complements", "imitates", "disgusts", "praises"],
    answer: "praises",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrases that's asterisked.",
    question:
      "The girl is angry with her friend who had *ensnared* her into this relationship.",
    options: ["tricked", "encouraged", "influenced", "forced"],
    answer: "tricked",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrases that's asterisked.",
    question: "Their new house was roofed with *corrugated* sheets.",
    options: ["folded", "iron", "aluminium", "corrupted"],
    answer: "iron",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrases that's asterisked.",
    question:
      "The stockbroker said it was an *astute* move to sell the shares then.",
    options: ["a bad", "a shrewd", "an unprofitable", "an insincere"],
    answer: "a shrewd",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrases that's asterisked.",
    question:
      "The principal described Oche as the most *tactful* person he had ever worked with.",
    options: ["passionate", "discrete", "hard-working", "innovative"],
    answer: "discrete",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrases that's asterisked.",
    question: "The old woman is suffering from *dementia*.",
    options: ["lucidity", "senility", "insanity", "sagacity"],
    answer: "senility",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrases that's asterisked.",
    question: "Some drugs have *deleterious* effect on a child’s development.",
    options: ["debilitating", "helpful", "harmful", "healing"],
    answer: "harmful",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrases that's asterisked.",
    question: "Fila has always described as *belligerent*.",
    options: ["beautiful", "attractive", "combative", "innocent"],
    answer: "combative",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrases that's asterisked.",
    question: "Laraba saw a *forlorn* little figure sitting outside the class.",
    options: [
      "wise and intelligent",
      "lonely and unhappy",
      "smart and healthy",
      "short and ugly",
    ],
    answer: "lonely and unhappy",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrases that's asterisked.",
    question:
      "The circular *supersedes* all previous correspondence on the matter.",
    options: ["supports", "displaces", "eliminates", "circumvents"],
    answer: "displaces",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrases that's asterisked.",
    question: "Her problem was *exacerbated* by the loss of her father.",
    options: ["exaggerated", "solved", "aggravated", "infuriated"],
    answer: "aggravated",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the word that is opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question:
      "The warring communities were *coerced* into negotiating a settlement.",
    options: ["driven", "compelled", "persuaded", "pressured"],
    answer: "persuaded",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the word that is opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "His father served as a *mercenary* in the army.",
    options: ["preacher", "regular", "recruit", "officer"],
    answer: "regular",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the word that is opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "Jummai is *cruel* to her husband.",
    options: ["harsh", "brutal", "passionate", "ferocious"],
    answer: "passionate",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the word that is opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "The teacher who beat the student was treated with *mercy*.",
    options: ["disrespect", "contempt", "vengeance", "kindness"],
    answer: "kindness",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the word that is opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "His wife hated his *garrulous* attitude.",
    options: ["outspoken", "unfriendly", "reticent", "thoughtful"],
    answer: "reticent",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the word that is opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "Agoshito is a *callow* youth; said the teacher.",
    options: ["an ignorant", "an experienced", "an idle", "an organized"],
    answer: "an experienced",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the word that is opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "What you are asking me to do is a *herculean* task.",
    options: ["a strenuous", "a demanding", "a lovely", "an easy"],
    answer: "an easy",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the word that is opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "Nkechi was a *novice* when she was first employed.",
    options: ["manager", "clerk", "supervisor", "professional"],
    answer: "professional",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the word that is opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "‘I do not trust him‘ he said, in a rare moment of *candour*.",
    options: ["reproach", "dishonesty", "frankness", "fairness"],
    answer: "dishonesty",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the word that is opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "Mrs. Akunilo looks *anaemic* today.",
    options: ["strange", "sick", "weak", "strong"],
    answer: "strong",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the word that is opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "It is *inconceivable* that the sun shone in the night.",
    options: ["credible", "unthinkable", "impossible", "contestable"],
    answer: "credible",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the word that is opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question:
      "She only gives a *superficial* impression of warmth and friendliness.",
    options: ["a strong", "a fake", "a deep", "an unrealistic"],
    answer: "a deep",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the word that is opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question:
      "As a *prudent* businessman, Adayi does not leave anything to chance.",
    options: ["a frugal", "shrewd", "careless", "unsuccessful"],
    answer: "careless",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the word that is opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "His *antipathy* affected the growth of his business.",
    options: ["hatred", "receptiveness", "loyalty", "hostility"],
    answer: "loyalty",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each of the questions choose the word that is opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question:
      "Okonkwo’s *lethal* right foot did the magic in the football match.",
    options: ["weak", "wicked", "fat", "harmless"],
    answer: "harmless",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each question choose the option that best completes the gap.",
    question: "When his car tyre ….. on the way, he did not know what to do.",
    options: ["has burst", "had burst", "bursted", "burst"],
    answer: "burst",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each question choose the option that best completes the gap.",
    question:
      "Lami’s father …. As a gardener when he was young, but now he is a driver.",
    options: ["had been working", "use to work", "has worked", "used to work"],
    answer: "used to work",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each question choose the option that best completes the gap.",
    question: "……. He switches on the light, the shadow disappears.",
    options: ["whenever", "except", "since", "until"],
    answer: "whenever",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each question choose the option that best completes the gap.",
    question:
      "It is important that you clear the refuse in front of your house every ……",
    options: ["fourtnight", "fortnight", "fourthnight", "forthnight"],
    answer: "fortnight",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each question choose the option that best completes the gap.",
    question:
      "The policemen became suspicious as the hoodlums…… in their office.",
    options: ["ferreted", "ferreted", "ferreted about", "ferreted about"],
    answer: "ferreted about",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each question choose the option that best completes the gap.",
    question: "Suara needn’t come with us...?",
    options: ["does she", "will she", "can she", "need she"],
    answer: "will she",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each question choose the option that best completes the gap.",
    question: "Unoka…. the whole house to find his missing wristwatch.",
    options: ["scourged", "scoured", "scored", "scouted"],
    answer: "scoured",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each question choose the option that best completes the gap.",
    question: "Ife asked me....",
    options: [
      "what time it was",
      "what is it by my time",
      "what time is it",
      "what time it is",
    ],
    answer: "what time it was",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each question choose the option that best completes the gap.",
    question:
      "There are many ways to kill a rat, so we should be …. In our approach to the task ahead of us.",
    options: ["ecletic", "eclectic", "eclektic", "eclectik"],
    answer: "eclectic",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each question choose the option that best completes the gap.",
    question: "Audu took these action purely…. His own career.",
    options: [
      "on furtherance of",
      "in furtherance of",
      "to furtherance in",
      "in furtherance with",
    ],
    answer: "in furtherance of",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each question choose the option that best completes the gap.",
    question: "Here is Mr. Odumusu who teaches English … in our school.",
    options: [
      "pronuntiation",
      "pronounciation",
      "pronunciation",
      "pronountiation",
    ],
    answer: "pronunciation",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each question choose the option that best completes the gap.",
    question: "Instead of… she lied.",
    options: ["pleading", "her to plead", "her pleading", "plead"],
    answer: "pleading",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each question choose the option that best completes the gap.",
    question: "Of the three girls, Uka is the….",
    options: ["so much notorious", "notorious", "naught", "naughtiest"],
    answer: "naughtiest",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each question choose the option that best completes the gap.",
    question:
      "I wonder how he will … being absent from school for a long time.",
    options: ["make in", "make up", "make off", "make out"],
    answer: "make up",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each question choose the option that best completes the gap.",
    question: "Please sit on the…",
    options: ["carier", "career", "carrier", "carrear"],
    answer: "carrier",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each question choose the option that best completes the gap.",
    question:
      "I want to … his chance to acquaint you with the latest development.",
    options: ["size", "seize", "sieze", "cease"],
    answer: "seize",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each question choose the option that best completes the gap.",
    question: "Getting a well-paid job nowadays is on….. task.",
    options: ["utmost", "upbeat", "uphill", "upfield"],
    answer: "uphill",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each question choose the option that best completes the gap.",
    question: "The secretary has no right to … my affairs.",
    options: ["spy from", "meddle in", "toy at", "complain into"],
    answer: "meddle in",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each question choose the option that best completes the gap.",
    question: "Bola studiously avoided… the question.",
    options: ["parrying", "answering", "projecting", "destroying"],
    answer: "answering",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "In each question choose the option that best completes the gap.",
    question:
      "The school authority dismissed him for …. But I won’t tell you about it yet.",
    options: ["certain reason", "a reason", "more reason", "a certain reason"],
    answer: "a certain reason",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the appropriate stress pattern from the option. The syllables are written in capital letters.",
    question: "Termination",
    options: ["terminaTION", "TERmination", "termiNAtion", "terMInation"],
    answer: "TERmination",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the appropriate stress pattern from the option. The syllables are written in capital letters.",
    question: "Meditative",
    options: ["meDItative", "mediTAtive", "Meditative", "meditaTIVE"],
    answer: "meDItative",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the appropriate stress pattern from the option. The syllables are written in capital letters.",
    question: "Suggestible",
    options: ["suggeSTIble", "Suggestible", "suGGEstible", "suggestible"],
    answer: "suggeSTIble",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "The word in capital letters has the emphatic stress. Choose the option to which the given sentence relates.",
    question: "Uche LOVES Toyota cars",
    options: [
      "Who loves Toyota cars?",
      "What brand of car does Uche love?",
      "Does Uche hate Toyota cars?",
      "Does Uche love bicycles?",
    ],
    answer: "What brand of car does Uche love?",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "The word in capital letters has the emphatic stress. Choose the option to which the given sentence relates.",
    question: "The POLICE arrested the suspect",
    options: [
      "Did the police placate the suspect?",
      "Who arrested the suspect?",
      "Who did the police arrest?",
      "Did the police arrest the suspect?",
    ],
    answer: "Who did the police arrest?",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "The word in capital letters has the emphatic stress. Choose the option to which the given sentence relates.",
    question: "Maiduguri is the CAPITAL of Borno state",
    options: [
      "Is Maiduguri the capital of Plateau state?",
      "Which state is Maiduguri the capital of?",
      "Is Maiduguri a town in Borno state?",
      "What is the capital of Borno state?",
    ],
    answer: "What is the capital of Borno state?",
  },
  {
    comprehension:
      "Religion in its various forms is very strong in Nigeria. In order words, Nigerian people are very religious. Most of them believe that there is an unseen supernatural world, apart from the natural world we see around us. This other world is inhabited by beings who are the source of our knowledge of good and evil. They watch and judge us and if we offend them they may have to be appeased with prayers and sacrifices. Certain individuals in the natural world - priest, prophets, and diviners – are believed to be endowed with special powers to make contact with the other world. These individuals lay down ceremonies or rituals which must be observed if due honour is to be paid to the unseen beings. The religious beliefs and practices of Nigerians can be classified under three main headings: Traditional religion, Islam, and Christianity. In this passage, our focus is on Traditional Religion. Traditional or indigenous religion continues to exert a strong influence on many people’s mind partly because of its association with their birth places and families. Each ethnic group has its own religious traditions, and these are often linked to some sacred spots in the ethnic homeland. Yet the various traditional religions have much in common: a remote but benevolent high god; under him, a number of lesser gods who interact with mankind; and below them various spirits who inhabit natural objects (trees, streams, rocks, etc.); below them again, and closest to living men and women, the spirits of the ancestors. In Yoruba tradition, for example, there are more than 400 lesser deities presided over by the high god, Olorun. Because he is remote from mankind, shrines are not built to him and worship is not offered to him directly. The lesser gods, on the other hand, are the subject of special cults, each with its own priest and devotees. Eshu, the messenger of the Gods; Ifa, the god of divination; Shango, the god of thunder, and so on. Traditional religion was also strong in other parts of Nigeria. In Igbo Traditional religion, there were fewer gods. Although there was a remote high god, the most important figure was Ala or Ani, the goddess of the earth. In Hausa land, traditional religion has largely gone underground owing to the influence of Islam, but belief in the existence of ‘Bori‘ spirits and their power to possess people, especially women, is strong in some areas. Each spirit is associated with a certain type of behaviour, which is manifested by the possessed individual. Divination – the discovery of what is unknown or is yet to happen by supernatural or magical means – is an important element of traditional religion. It is often one of the functions of ‘medicine men’ or ‘herbalists’. In Igboland, there also used to be several oracles which people consulted in order to seek solutions to their problems. With the coming of Christianity, their influence has however waned, but in areas like Arochukwu and Okija, the influence of such oracles is still strongly felt.",
    instruction: "From the passage, answer the following questions.",
    questions: [
      {
        question: "From the passage, one can say that all ethnic groups have",
        options: [
          "different traditional religions with some elements of similarities",
          "completely different religious practices",
          "the same traditional religion",
          "the same religious manifestations with common deities",
        ],
        answer:
          "different traditional religions with some elements of similarities",
      },
      {
        question:
          "According to the first paragraph, Nigerians believe that the",
        options: [
          "supernatural and natural world co-exist",
          "natural and supernatural worlds are antagonistic",
          "supernatural world controls the natural world",
          "supernatural world exploits the natural world",
        ],
        answer: "supernatural world controls the natural world",
      },
      {
        question: "Traditional religion has waned in Nigeria owing to the",
        options: [
          "influence of Islam over Bori spirits",
          "influence of Christianity over local oracles",
          "decline of the interest in traditional religions",
          "influence of non-traditional religions",
        ],
        answer: "influence of non-traditional religions",
      },
      {
        question:
          "Which factor is common to all traditional religions as mentioned in the passage?",
        options: ["Prayer only.", "Divination.", "Sacrifice only.", "Rituals."],
        answer: "Divination.",
      },
    ],
  },
  {
    comprehension:
      "Recently, literally research reveals that Nigerians hardly have time to read. In essence, the reading culture in Nigeria is now at a low ebb. It is disturbing, however, that the few Nigerians that read concentrate on foreign books more than indigenous productions. Most Nigerian authors of novels, storybooks, fiction, and non-fiction series have decried, on different occasions, their woes. They were bitter in the way most owners of bookshops and publishers treat them. It was gathered that most renowned bookshops in Nigeria hardly sell books written by indigenous authors. They preferred to stock foreign books. When contacted by DAILY INDEPENDENT, the general manager of a popular bookstore in Lagos Island declared that most bookshops preferred to stock foreign books because of higher demands for them. The question that bothers most Nigerian authors is, while their overseas counterparts are being rewarded with great international honors, why are Nigerians not according them such recognition in their own country? Recently, Nigerian novelist Chimamanda Ngozi Adichie won the 2007 Orange Prize Award, the literary world’s top award for fiction in English written by women. The award carries a prize tag of $30,000. It was reported in Publishers Weekly, *Half of a Yellow Sun*, the book that earned her the award, was profoundly gripping. According to the reviewer, the book is a ‘transcendent novel of many descriptive triumph, most notably its diction of the impact of war brutalities on peasants and intellectuals alike. It is a searing history in fictional form, intensely evocative and immensely absorbing’. Chinua Achebe, ‘Father of Modern African Literature’, also won the second ever Man Booker International Prize of ‘£60,000’ with his first novel *Things Fall Apart*, published in 1958. When Professor Wole Soyinka won the Nobel Prize for Literature in 1986, the fame confirmed the relevance of Nigerians in the world of classical excellence. Ben Okri won the 1991 Booker Prize with his work, *The Famished Road*, and the world celebrated Nigeria as the giant of Africa. It was also gathered that most of the publishers hurriedly produce books and in the process marred their good contents. Most of the books are not properly edited and actually become substandard when compared with the foreign products. The extent to which book publishing standards have fallen in Nigeria is alarming. Often Nigerian publishers have been blamed for this. It is instructive that none of the books mentioned had been published in Nigeria. It was discovered that most students in tertiary institutions depend on dictations from their lecturers and/or handouts. A science lecturer in one of the Nigerian universities, who had been a victim of handout sales scandal, told DAILY INDEPENDENT the reality of campus challenges in relation to books. ‘I was to dictate notes slowly to students who hung on every word in the absence of textbooks in a library that had, to all intents and purposes, stopped buying new books when the local currency devalued. But what other alternative does one have?",
    instruction: "From the passage, answer the following questions.",
    questions: [
      {
        question: "It can be inferred from the passage that",
        options: [
          "Nigerians have access to foreign books only",
          "Nigerian undergraduates do not read textbooks",
          "Nigerians read foreign and indigenous books alike",
          "Nigerians read mostly foreign books",
        ],
        answer: "Nigerians read mostly foreign books",
      },
      {
        question:
          "The reason for lack of indigenous books in most renowned bookshops, according to the passage,",
        options: [
          "Nigerians prefer reading foreign books",
          "foreign books attract more buyers",
          "indigenous books are sometimes not available",
          "the low quality of indigenous books",
        ],
        answer: "foreign books attract more buyers",
      },
      {
        question:
          "The expression 'profoundly gripping' that earned her the award means that the book",
        options: [
          "is highly interesting and captures attention",
          "is of high quality to the writer",
          "attracts many indigenous and foreign readers",
          "is widely acknowledged by many authors",
        ],
        answer: "is highly interesting and captures attention",
      },
      {
        question:
          "The university science lecturer gives his reason for issuing handouts as",
        options: [
          "lack of teaching aids among students",
          "low purchasing power",
          "low quality of books",
          "lack of sufficient time",
        ],
        answer: "low purchasing power",
      },
      {
        question: "A suitable title for this passage is",
        options: [
          "Nigerian Literary Writers",
          "Nigerian Publishers and International Awards",
          "Poor Reading Culture in Nigeria",
          "Why Nigerian Lecturers Sell Handouts",
        ],
        answer: "Poor Reading Culture in Nigeria",
      },
    ],
  },
  {
    comprehension:
      "It is said that experience is the best teacher, but to learn consciously through wisdom may even be a better and more convenient way. To learn by experience is to learn from mistakes. It means you have burnt your fingers and now ‘your eyes are open’. This is a tough, costly and inconvenient way to learn. Rather than leaving our learning to experience, why do we not learn consciously through wisdom? We can learn by consciously going out of our way to acquire knowledge and wisdom rather than leave our learning to chance. Surely, we can learn from mistakes but why wait till when we make mistakes before we learn? We should give more premium to learning by wisdom than by experience. This will involve one making up ones’ mind to be decisive in learning. We must decide to learn consciously and not necessarily from negative experiences. The first step is to realize that life is simply the outcomes and outplay of decisions. Our life now is the sum total of our decisions and our future will be determined by our decision of today. If we decide to learn today, we are not likely to make mistakes and when we do not make mistakes. Experience need not to be our best teacher. To avoid making experience our best teacher will take more than a decision. We must couple our decision with a complete and wholehearted devotion. We must be resolved, resolute and resilient in our bid to learn by wisdom and not necessarily by experience. This is crucial because situations and circumstances will want us to make a detour and leave our learning and life to chance. We must therefore be disciplined to remain with our resolve to make a clean break with experience as our best teacher. Discipline in this regard means learning something new every day by wisdom rather than experience. It means consciously getting better by the day in your chosen field. Discipline will demand taking advantage of every learning opportunity that comes our way. It will mean we must pay the price for learning by wisdom – invest in books, magazines, seminars and other means by which we may become wiser. It is much easier and cheaper to learn consciously by wisdom than to learn by experience. When we learn by experience, the deed is done and we are just picking up the pieces – learning in regret how to avoid such predicament next time. Consider the child who grasps a burning coal, he has learned the hard way through the painful experience, but his fingers will remain burnt. Thus, the saying, that experience is the best teacher, may not be justifiable after all.",
    instruction:
      "Read the passage carefully and answer the questions that follow.",
    questions: [
      {
        question:
          "The attitude of the writer of the passage can best be described as",
        options: ["objective", "critical", "non-committal", "emotional"],
        answer: "critical",
      },
      {
        question: "It can be deduced from the passage that",
        options: [
          "all experiences are best teachers",
          "learning through pains is better",
          "experience is superior to wisdom",
          "wise thoughts are more desirable than experience",
        ],
        answer: "wise thoughts are more desirable than experience",
      },
      {
        question:
          "Which of the following states is true according to the passage?",
        options: [
          "man must make mistakes in order to survive",
          "the totality of our actions should be decided by our judgement",
          "if we do not make mistakes, experience must be our teacher",
          "our future would be judged by our past mistakes",
        ],
        answer:
          "the totality of our actions should be decided by our judgement",
      },
      {
        question: "According to the passage, we must be disciplined to",
        options: [
          "make experience our best teacher in reality",
          "learn from experience in future",
          "choose the learning opportunity that comes our way",
          "decide against making experience our teacher",
        ],
        answer: "choose the learning opportunity that comes our way",
      },
      {
        question:
          "The phrase a complete and wholehearted devotion, as used in the passage, means",
        options: [
          "acting without doubt",
          "learning with tension",
          "learning without pains",
          "teaching with ease",
        ],
        answer: "acting without doubt",
      },
    ],
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Select the option that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question:
      "Hardworking students must not have a finger in very pie at school.",
    options: [
      "Hardworking students must not have a role to play in most activities in the school",
      "Only hardworking students must participate in all activities in the school",
      "Hardworking students do not participate in all activities in the school",
      "Hardworking students must ask others to participate in school activities",
    ],
    answer:
      "Hardworking students must not have a role to play in most activities in the school",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Select the option that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question:
      "The vice chancellor is riding the crest of the last quarter of his administration.",
    options: [
      "The vice chancellor enjoys the acknowledgement of the success of his administration",
      "The vice chancellor does not enjoy the people’s criticism of his administration",
      "The vice chancellor hopes to overcome soon, the poor comments on his administration",
      "The vice chancellor does not talk of his successes in office",
    ],
    answer:
      "The vice chancellor enjoys the acknowledgement of the success of his administration",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Select the option that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question: "She was absolved by the court from the charge.",
    options: [
      "She was convicted for the charge",
      "She was blamed and charged to court",
      "Her case was resolved by the court",
      "She was declared free from the charge",
    ],
    answer: "She was declared free from the charge",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Select the option that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question: "The landlord is fond of throwing his weight about.",
    options: [
      "The landlord likes healthy exercise",
      "The landlord is overweight",
      "The landlord gives orders to people",
      "The landlord is respected by his tenants",
    ],
    answer: "The landlord gives orders to people",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Select the option that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question:
      "The company ought to have issued warrants for one billion shares.",
    options: [
      "The company has issued one billion shares",
      "The management expected the company to issue more than one billion shares",
      "Members of the company bought less than one billion shares",
      "The company did not issue one billion shares",
    ],
    answer: "The company did not issue one billion shares",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Select the option that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question:
      "He needed not to have played in the position of quarterback in the volleyball.",
    options: [
      "He participated in the game in his unusual position",
      "Nobody expected him to have participated in the game",
      "He wanted to play in a position other than the one he was offered",
      "Someone did not want him to play in the position that he played",
    ],
    answer: "Nobody expected him to have participated in the game",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Select the option that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question: "I wouldn’t have responded to his rude talk, if I were you.",
    options: [
      "The advice was taken by the respondent, so he did not respond to the talk",
      "The adviser put himself in the respondent’s position, so he did not respond to the talk",
      "The respondent replied to the speaker’s talk, although he ought not to have done so",
      "What was advisable was that the respondent gave it back to the speaker",
    ],
    answer:
      "The respondent replied to the speaker’s talk, although he ought not to have done so",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Select the option that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question: "He could not speak out because he had a feet of clay.",
    options: [
      "His feet was muddy",
      "He was weak and cowardly",
      "He was clumsy and lazy",
      "He was shy and timid",
    ],
    answer: "He was weak and cowardly",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Select the option that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question:
      "The player wasted a golden opportunity during the penalty shoot-out.",
    options: [
      "The player hit the bar",
      "The player did not score the shot",
      "The player scored the shot that made them win the gold cup",
      "Instead of a silver cup, they received the golden one",
    ],
    answer: "The player did not score the shot",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Select the option that best explains the information conveyed in the sentence.",
    question:
      "As far as Abu is concerned, Mero should be given fifty naira at the most.",
    options: [
      "All Abu is saying is that Mero probably deserves more than fifty naira and not less",
      "All Abu is concerned with is that Mero should be given nothing more than fifty naira",
      "In Abu’s estimation, Mero merits not more than fifty naira",
      "In Abu’s opinion, Mero deserves fifty naira or probably more",
    ],
    answer: "In Abu’s estimation, Mero merits not more than fifty naira",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "As an *idiot*, the boy is weak in class.",
    options: ["a deviant", "a dunce", "an expert", "a genius"],
    answer: "a genius",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "We were shocked by the news that he had lost the *money*.",
    options: ["astonished", "disconcerted", "unconcerned", "surprised"],
    answer: "unconcerned",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "The principal was advised to be *flexible* on critical issues.",
    options: ["livid", "cautious", "evasive", "rigid"],
    answer: "rigid",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "Bola always looks *sober*.",
    options: ["excited", "serious", "worried", "helpless"],
    answer: "excited",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "Dupe was promoted for her *efficiency*.",
    options: ["ability", "incompetence", "inconsistency", "rudeness"],
    answer: "incompetence",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question:
      "The management wants to consider her *reticent* behaviour in due course.",
    options: ["disapproving", "disciplinarian", "contemplative", "loquacious"],
    answer: "loquacious",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "Election process often become *volatile*.",
    options: ["calm", "strange", "sudden", "latent"],
    answer: "calm",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question:
      "Oche entered the principal’s office in a rather *abrasive* manner.",
    options: ["gentle", "rude", "lackadaisical", "indifferent"],
    answer: "gentle",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question:
      "Otokpa is a member of the *ad hoc* committee on stock acquisition.",
    options: ["improvised", "formal", "temporary", "fact-finding"],
    answer: "formal",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "His gift to the poor was always *infinitesimal*.",
    options: ["large", "small", "supportive", "shameful"],
    answer: "large",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question:
      "The economist concluded that several factors have been *adduced* to explain the fall in the birth rate.",
    options: ["affirmed", "diffused", "mentioned", "refuted"],
    answer: "refuted",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question:
      "The presidential system is an *antidote* to some political ailments.",
    options: ["an answer", "a reply", "an injury", "an obstacle"],
    answer: "an injury",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "Ola thought that her father was very *callous*.",
    options: ["parlous", "compassionate", "wicked", "cheerful"],
    answer: "compassionate",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "He was very much respected, though he had no *temporal* power.",
    options: ["spiritual", "mundane", "permanent", "ephemeral"],
    answer: "mundane",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option opposite in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "The way the worship was organized was rather *hit-and-miss*.",
    options: ["systematic", "hasty", "slow", "funny"],
    answer: "systematic",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question:
      "Some men will continue to cause offences until they are given a taste of their own *medicine*.",
    options: ["placated", "revenged on", "recompensed for", "cured"],
    answer: "revenged on",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question:
      "Okibe was rusticated for his *derogated* remark about the principal.",
    options: ["complimentary", "unsavoury", "unwarranted", "lacklustre"],
    answer: "unsavoury",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question:
      "Justice is difficult to enforce because people are unwilling to accept any loss of *sovereignty*.",
    options: ["autonomy", "position", "leadership", "kingdom"],
    answer: "autonomy",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "There are still *virtuous* women in our society today.",
    options: ["clever", "upright", "devilish", "intelligent"],
    answer: "upright",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "The type of response is typical of a *lazy* teacher.",
    options: ["symptomatic", "characteristic", "universal", "incontestable"],
    answer: "characteristic",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "Akin is an *inveterate* gambler.",
    options: [
      "a selfish and self-centred",
      "an extremely unlucky but popular",
      "an incurable but fearful",
      "a long time and incorrigible",
    ],
    answer: "a long time and incorrigible",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question:
      "He was too *petrified* to give the closing remarks at the conference.",
    options: ["frightened", "delighted", "agitated", "happy"],
    answer: "frightened",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question:
      "During a particular time of the day, the road *shimmers* in the heat.",
    options: ["darkens", "lightens", "shines", "beams"],
    answer: "shines",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "Every human being is *vulnerable* to communicable diseases.",
    options: ["liable", "lifted", "immuned", "closed"],
    answer: "liable",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "Mariam looks rather *furtive* to Shehu.",
    options: ["intoxicated", "unfriendly", "sad", "sly"],
    answer: "sly",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "The student’s union leader delivered his speech *extempore*.",
    options: ["out-of-hand", "off the cuff", "accurately", "courageously"],
    answer: "off the cuff",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question:
      "His story gave us an *inkling* of what he passed through during the strike.",
    options: ["a possible idea", "a taste", "a summary", "the right view"],
    answer: "a possible idea",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "These policies have been *expoused* by the ruling party.",
    options: ["condemned", "rejected", "supported", "outlined"],
    answer: "supported",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question:
      "We must not *foreclose* reconciliation as the purpose of his trip.",
    options: ["exclude", "consider", "underestimate", "forgo"],
    answer: "exclude",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Choose the option nearest in meaning to the word or phrase that's asterisked.",
    question: "Her finding *exploded* widely held beliefs about learning.",
    options: ["challenged", "debunked", "projected", "confirmed"],
    answer: "debunked",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Choose the option that best complete the gap(s).",
    question: "He was both a writer and a politician, but he was better __.",
    options: ["as if", "like", "as", "to be"],
    answer: "as",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Choose the option that best complete the gap(s).",
    question: "Vacancies in the company will be notified by __.",
    options: ["bulletin", "publication", "publicity", "advertisement"],
    answer: "advertisement",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Choose the option that best complete the gap(s).",
    question:
      "The driver was short of petrol, so he __ down the hills with the engine switched off.",
    options: ["glided", "coasted", "wheeled", "taxied"],
    answer: "glided",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Choose the option that best complete the gap(s).",
    question: "He started his career as an __.",
    options: ["auxillary", "auxilliary", "auxilary", "auxiliary"],
    answer: "auxiliary",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Choose the option that best complete the gap(s).",
    question:
      "His many years of success in legal practice, __ didn’t come without challenges.",
    options: ["indeed", "but", "in spite of it all", "however"],
    answer: "indeed",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Choose the option that best complete the gap(s).",
    question:
      "One should be careful how __ behaves in the public, shouldn’t __.",
    options: ["one/one", "he/he", "she/one", "one/he"],
    answer: "one/he",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Choose the option that best complete the gap(s).",
    question: "__ a good leader must have two characteristics.",
    options: [
      "First and formost",
      "First and formust",
      "First and farmost",
      "First and foremost",
    ],
    answer: "First and foremost",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Choose the option that best complete the gap(s).",
    question: "We visited his house __ three times.",
    options: ["like", "for like", "about", "for about"],
    answer: "about",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Choose the option that best complete the gap(s).",
    question: "She was __ the verge of tears.",
    options: ["at", "on", "by", "with"],
    answer: "at",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Choose the option that best complete the gap(s).",
    question: "Everyone makes mistakes occasionally; nobody is __.",
    options: ["incorrigible", "Imperfect", "Infallible", "indestructible"],
    answer: "Infallible",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Choose the option that best complete the gap(s).",
    question: "The woman would not part with her __ pot.",
    options: [
      "discarded earthen black",
      "discarded black earthen",
      "earthen discarded black",
      "black earthen discarded",
    ],
    answer: "discarded black earthen",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Choose the option that best complete the gap(s).",
    question: "We stood up when the principal came in __.",
    options: ["isn’t it", "didn’t we", "not so", "did us"],
    answer: "didn’t we",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Choose the option that best complete the gap(s).",
    question: "The professor of __ medicine has __.",
    options: [
      "vetinary / unraveled",
      "vertrinary/unravelled",
      "veterinary/unraveled",
      "veterinary/unravelled",
    ],
    answer: "veterinary/unravelled",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Choose the option that best complete the gap(s).",
    question: "Her mother brought her some __.",
    options: ["clothes", "yards", "cloth", "clothing"],
    answer: "clothes",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Choose the option that best complete the gap(s).",
    question: "Many workers were __ as a result of the textile closure.",
    options: ["laid down", "laid off", "laid out", "laid up"],
    answer: "laid off",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Choose the option that best complete the gap(s).",
    question: "The driver died in the __ road accident.",
    options: ["fatal", "brutal", "serious", "pathetic"],
    answer: "fatal",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Choose the option that best complete the gap(s).",
    question:
      "__ your parents frown __ our friendship, we shouldn’t see each other anymore.",
    options: ["Because / over", "Since / at", "Although /at", "As / upon"],
    answer: "Since / at",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Choose the option that best complete the gap(s).",
    question:
      "For more productivity, the company is focusing attention on the possible __.",
    options: ["synergy", "tapping", "alignment", "arrangement"],
    answer: "tapping",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Choose the option that best complete the gap(s).",
    question: "__ she didn’t trust him, she married him.",
    options: ["After", "Much as", "Since", "Though"],
    answer: "Though",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Choose the option that best complete the gap(s).",
    question: "I wanted to know his political beliefs, so I asked him what __.",
    options: ["this was", "these are", "this is", "these were"],
    answer: "these were",
  },
];
